A Guide to the University of Virginia Commencement Addresses, 1911-2006
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
University of Virginia Commencement Addresses 1911-2006
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
RG-30/9/1.061
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These speeches were transferred to the University of Virginia Library, ca. 1957-2006, by University officials and have been combined under this new number on October 10, 2006. Persons involved in these transfers include: William H. Wranek, Alexander G. Gilliam, John Charles Thomas, Harland Harris, and Information Services.
Scope and Content
These files contain copies of speeches given at University of Virginia Commencement Exercises, approximately 40 items (1 Hollinger box), 1911-2006 (incomplete). Of special interest are the speeches by President Roosevelt ("the hand that held the dagger has struck it into the back of its neighbor"), 1940, and Edgar Shannon, 1970, on May Days and the student strike at the University of Virginia.
With the collection is a list of known commencement speakers, 1908-1989, compiled by then Assistant University Archivist Jeanne C. Pardee.
Arrangement
The speaker's name and title make up the file heading and all speeches are arranged in chronological order.
Contents List
- Edwin Anderson Alderman, President of University, 1911 (Folder 1)
- Edwin Anderson Alderman, President of University, 1920 (Folder 2)
- Edwin Anderson Alderman, President of University, 1926 (Folder 3)
- A. A. Hill, Philologist, 1939 (Folder 3a)
- Franklin Delano Roosevelt, President of the United States, 1940 (Folder 4)
- Marshall Field, 1941 (Folder 5)
- Honorable Colgate Whitehead Darden, Governor of Virginia, 1942 (Folder 6)
- Eric Allen Johnson, President of the United States Chamber of Commerce, 1943 (Folder 7)
- Staige Davis Blackford, [1945] (Folder 8)
- Honorable James William Fulbright, US Senator from Arkansas, 1947 (Folder 9)
- David E. Lilienthal, Chairman of the US Atomic Energy Commission, 1948 (Folder 10)
- Dr. Gilford Norman Ward, 1949 (Folder 11)
- Robert O. Nelson, Division Superintendent of Schools for Newport News, Virginia, 1952 (Folder 12)
- Honorable Colgate Whitehead Darden, 1956 (Folder 13)
- Dr. Gabriel Hauge, Special Assistant to the President of the United States, 1957 (Folder 14)
- Honorable Colgate Whitehead Darden, 1959 (Folder 15)
- Honorable Colgate Whitehead Darden, 1964 (Folder 16)
- Edgar F. Shannon Jr., President of the University, 1970 (Folder 17)
- William F. Buckley Jr., Editor of National Review, 1972 (Folder 18)
- Mrs. Lyndon B. Johnson (Lady Bird Johnson), 1973 (Folder 19)
- Edgar F. Shannon Jr., President of the University, 1974 (Folder 20)
- Honorable Mill E. Godwin Jr., Governor of Virginia, 1976 (Folder 21)
- Honorable James R. Schlesinger, Councellor to the President of the United States on Energy, 1977 (Folder 22)
- Honorable Thurgood Marshall, Associate Justice of the Supreme Court of the United States, 1978 (Folder 23)
- George H. W. Bush, Vice President of the United States 1981 (Folder 23a)
- Pete V. Domenici, United States Senator from New Mexico, 1982 (Folder 24)
- Charles S. Robb, Governor of Virginia, 1983 (Folder 25)
- Frank L. Hereford, President of the University, 1985 (Folder 26)
- Honorable Lawrence Douglas Wilder, Lieutenant Governor of Virginia, 1986 (Folder 27)
- Honorable John Paul Stevens, Associate Justice of the Supreme Court of the United States, 1988 (Folder 28)
- Honorable Gerald L. Baliles, Governor of Virginia, 1989 (Folder 29)
- Robert M. O'Neil, 1990 (Folder 30)
- W. Nathaniel Howell, 1991 (Folder 31)
- Honorable John Charles Thomas, 1992 (Folder 32)
- John Thomas Casteen III, President of the University, 1993 (Folder 33)
- George Allen, Governor of Virginia, 1994 (Folder 34)
- William Raspberry, 1995 (Folder 35)
- Kathryn C. Thornton, NASA Astronaut, 1996 (Folder 36)
- Hunter B. Andrews, Senator, 1997 (Folder 37)
- Jim Gilmore, Governor of Virginia, 1998 (Folder 38)
- Honorable Howard H. Baker Jr., 1999 (Folder 39)
- Timothy M. Kaine, Governor of Virginia, 2006 (Folder 40)